Guide to the Butler Family Papers, 1924-1987 MS 0984
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Butler Family Papers
1924-1987
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Frank, Janis Butler
MS 0984
.25 Linear Feet 1 box
One box of programs, news clippings, event materials, and family history materials, including a digitized memoir and news clippings, document the Butler family between 1924 to 1987.
Biographical / Historical
Jacob "Jake" H. Butler was born in Buffalo, Texas, on March 7, 1893, to Louis Butler and his wife whose name is unknown because Jake's mother died when he was quite young. He was one of 6 children: Jacob, Libbie, Leo, Sidney, Myron, and Nathan. Jake, his brother Leo, and his sister Libbie were sent to the Jewish Orphan Home in New Orleans, as his father could not take care of all the children. In 1902 Jake was able to rejoin his family in Houston; his father remarried Augusta Asher Butler, who had three children of her own. Jacob only attended school up to his middle school years, and got a job with the Houston Chronicle sweeping and taking calls after hours. He worked through the ranks to become the Manager of the Classified Department of the Houston Chronicle, and later was promoted to Business Manager of the Houston Chronicle, and eventually to Vice President.
Jacob was married to Della Lazarus Butler in 1917. They had one son, Myron Jack Butler, who was drafted by the professional hockey team Chicago Blackhawks after high school, but instead chose to attend Northwestern University and went into journalism. Jack worked at the Houston Chronicle like his father, and worked up to become Business Manager. Jack married Melanie Jones Butler in 1942 and they had two daughters, Pam and Jan.
Jacob Butler died June 20, 1973 after a long illness.
Content Description
One box of programs, event materials, and family history materials, including a digitized memoir and news clippings, document the Butler family between 1924 to 1987.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials open for research.
Stored off-site at the Library Service Center and requires 24-hour notice for retrieval. Please contact the Woodson Research Center at 713-348-2586 or woodson@rice.edu for more information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Janis Butler Frank donated the papers in April 2021.
Arrangement
The materials in this collection have been arranged in one series: Series I: General.
Index Terms
Subjects
Jews and Jewish life
Document Types
Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Programs (Publications)
Subjects (Persons)
Frank, Janis Butler
- Series I: General, 1924-1987
  - M.M. Society Charity Dance Program, 1924-1938 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Sigma Alpha Rho Dance Programs, 1937-1941 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Aleph Zadik Alpeh Jr. B'nai Brith Programs, 1938-1941 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - BZB Sorority Valentine Dance Program, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Junior Hadassah Show and Dance Program, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Ramblers Club Charity Dance Program, 1939-1940 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Congregation Adath Emeth Ball Program, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Delta Epsilon Beta Dance Program, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Butler Family History, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Memoirs by Libbie Butler, 1987